# HASSAAN ALI WATTOO

♦ Seattle, WA — Open to Remote

hassaanaliw@gmail.com ♦ linkedin.com/in/hassaanwattoo/ ♦ wattoo.me

# **OBJECTIVE**

Software Engineer with 2+ years of experience at Microsoft, specializing in backend development and performance improvements for scalable data services. I place great emphasis on technical fundamentals and operational excellence in order to keep services up and always available.

# **EDUCATION**

Bachelors of Engineering, University of Michigan

2017 - 2021

Relevant Coursework: Algorithms, Web Systems, Operating Systems, Search Engine Design

**GPA:** 3.63

## **SKILLS**

• Programming Languages: C#, C++, Python, Javascript

- Web Development: HTML/CSS, React, Flask, Django, Express
- Testing and Deployment: XUnit Testing, Azure Load Testing, JMeter
- Scripting: Bash, PowerShell

#### EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer

Aug 2021 - Present Seattle, WA

Microsoft

- Took over a failing analytics pipeline, and reduced job failure rate by over 45%. Decreased data latency from the order of days to hours. This led to a cost reduction of several thousands of dollars, and enabled executives to make financial decisions more accurately and quickly.
- Led research, design and development for the core data model used by a brand new Microsoft service.
- Developed a data simulator, allowing us to simulate data being streamed by thousands of users, tailored to customer scenarios. Resulted in several high impact performance issues being profiled and resolved before release.
- Developed scalable real-time business alerting system using PowerAutomate, reducing incident detection time for customers, thereby enhancing their ability to take swift action.
- Addressed code quality issues by introducing end-to-end XUnit testing suite for the core service API, resulting in over 98% coverage for all customer scenarios and greatly reducing reported customer issues.

# Managing Web Developer

Nov 2018 - Jan 2020

Ann Arbor, MI

The Michigan Daily

- Responsible for ideating new projects, managing existing products, and coordinating a SCRUM team of 25 designers and developers.
- Created and released GradeGuide, a grade distribution visualizer. Recieved 100,000+ visits in its first year.
- Led the development and release of a React Native mobile app to deliver Michigan Daily news to iOS devices.

### PROJECTS

# GradeGuide

- Built the first Grade Distribution visualizer for University of Michigan to aid students in choosing courses.
- Created Flask API and MySQL Database structure, focusing on speed optimization and caching of responses.
- Led marketing efforts and user studies to maximize user interaction. Drove over 100,000 uses in a calendar year.
- Developed frontend search system and course grade visualisations in ReactJS and D3.js.